Harold Seidman Papers 1984.0031
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Harold Seidman Papers
undated, 1930-1980
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0031
12.85 Linear Feet
Professor of Political Science at the University of Connecticut from 1971 to 1984, Seidman was involved with the creation of the Marshall Plan and the development of the European Recovery Corporation under President Truman. He played a major role in the passage of the St. Lawrence Seaway Project, testified on the admission of Alaska and Hawaii into statehood and on the government's role towards the territories of Guam, Puerto Rico, the Panama Canal and Ryker Island.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
Harold Seidman> donated the bulk of his papers in 1982. Additional materials were donated at the time of his retirement as Professor of Political Science in 1984.
Arrangement
Series I: Bureau of the Budget (1937-1973) consists of subject files of materials collected by Seidman while working within this government agency. Materials include correspondence concerning various projects with which Seidman was involved, reports prepared for official use, copies of Congressional bills and hearing testimony, as well as publications and press releases on various topics. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series II: Public Administration Consulting (1968-1979) consists of subject files of materials used by Seidman while consulting on various topics, particularly government organization. Materials include correspondence and memoranda, reports and drafts of reports, publications and copies of Congressional bills. Seidman worked on the Watergate Reorganization and Reform Act and was a member of President' Nixon's ASH Council on Executive Office Reorganization. Files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Series III: Writings (1930-1980) contain publications written by or about Seidman. As a member of The Nation staff, Seidman wrote editorials. A copy of his Master's thesis, "The International Implications of Italian Fascism," and a copy of an oral history transcript, located in the Truman Presidential Library, is included. Materials are arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Research Files (undated) contains the working papers for Seidman's book, Politics, Position and Power. Also included are research materials gathered by the author. The folders reflect Seidman's folder headings and order.
Series V: Personal (undated) consists of correspondence, copies of lectures given by Seidman, newspaper clippings, photographs and memorabilia collected by Seidman over the years.
Biography
Harold Seidman was born in Brooklyn, NY on 2 July 1911. He attended Brown University for both his undergraduate (A.B., 1934) and graduate degrees (M.A., 1935). During the summers, Seidman worked on the editorial staff of the magazine, The Nation. In 1938, he entered the Ph.D. program at Yale University while working for the City of New York's Department of Investigation, under Thomas E. Dewey. From 1940 until 1943, Seidman was awarded the Ph.D. in Government and continued to work for the Department of Investigation, as Director of Research.
In 1943, Seidman became a Management Analyst with the U.S. Bureau of the Budget, as a member of the Government Organization Branch. While a member of the Bureau staff, Seidman was responsible for a variety of public policy issues. He was involved in the creation of the Marshall Plan and the development of the European Recovery Corporation under President Truman. He played a major role in the passage of the St. Lawrence Seaway Project, testified on the admission of Alaska and Hawaii into statehood and on the government's role towards the territories of Guam, Puerto Rico, the Panama Canal and Ryker Island. Seidman became Chief of the Government Organization Branch in 1961, under President Kennedy, and later Assistant Director of Management and Organization under President Johnson in 1964. He remained with the Bureau until 1968.
After retiring from government service in 1968, Seidman acted as a consultant to the government on numerous projects. He served on President Nixon's ASH Council on Executive Office Reorganization. He consulted for the government in Colombia, Guatemala, Iran, South Vietnam and Turkey. He continued to counsel the U.S. government on matters of government operations.
Seidman is a prolific writer. Between 1930 and 1984, he wrote articles and books on public administration, racketeering, and government organization. His articles have been published in scholarly journals. He also published two books, Labor Czars: A History of Labor Racketeering and Politics (1938) and Politics, Position and Power: The Dynamics of Federal Organization (1970).
Between 1952 and 1984, Seidman brought his varied government experiences to the classroom. He was a Lecturer at George Washington University (1952-1953), Visiting Professor at the University of Southern California (1962), Scholar-in-Residence at the National Academy of Public Administration (1969-1970), a Research Fellow, Visiting Lecturer and Visiting Professor at Leeds University (U.K., 1971-1975) and Professor in the Political Science department at the University of Connecticut (1971- 1984).
Scope and Content
The collection contains subject files, correspondence, memoranda, reports, press releases, publications, working papers for publications, lectures, clippings, photographs and memorabilia arranged into five series.
Labor unions--Corrupt practices; Notes; Labor unions; Monographs; Photocopies; Canals, Interoceanic.; Reconstruction (1939-1951); Statehood (American politics); Canals; Budget--Law and legislation; Europe (continent); Political science; Universities and colleges; Education; Economic assistance; Panama (nation); Racketeering; Oral histories (document genres); United States (nation); Nineteenth century; Educators; Interviews; Editors; Journalism; Connecticut (state); Federal government--Officials and employees; International relations; Saint Lawrence Seaway (navigation channel); Panama Canal (canal); Federal government; Administrative agencies; Photographs; Correspondence; Publications (documents); Alaska (state); Press releases; Hawaii (state)
- Series I: Bureau of the Budget, 1937-1973
  - Air Transport Association, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Alaska Omnibus Bill, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Bonneville Project Act, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committee Organization in the House, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Department of Consumers, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Defense Research Institutes, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Electronic Data Processing equipment, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - European Recovery Corporation, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Farm Credit Administration, 1948-1960 (Box 1, Folder 16-23)
  - Federal Credit Programs, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Federal Highways Commission, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Federal Council for Science & Technology, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Federal Tax Policy, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Government Corporations, 1937-1948 (Box 1, Folder 28-32)
  - Government Corporation Control Act, 1948-1961 (Box 1, Folder 33-37)
  - Guam, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hawaii Omnibus Bill, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 39-41)
  - Integovernmental Cooperation, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Intergovernmental Cooperation, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Marine Sciences Engineering & Resources Reorganization, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Maritime Administration, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Merchant Marine Study, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Missile Programs, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Mutualization of Government Lending and Insurance Agencies, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - National Advisory Council Reorganization, 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Organization & Cooperation of Foreign Economic Activities, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Organization of Federal Administrative Services, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Organization of Federal Banking Functions, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Panama Canal, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Panama Canal Company, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - President's Task Force on Governmental Reorganization, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Puerto Rico, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 56-58)
  - Reorganization of Executive Branch, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 59-60)
  - Reorganization Plan, 1950-1967 (Box 2, Folder 61-62)
  - Revenue Sharing, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - St. Lawrence Seaway Development, 1952-1961 (Box 2, Folder 64-72)
  - Small Business Subcontracting, 1965 (Box 2a, Folder 73)
  - Task Force on Improvement of Higher Civil Service, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Turkey, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 75-77)
  - United Nations Seminar, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Vietnam, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Water pollution, 1966, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 80-81)
- Series II: Public Administration Consulting, 1968-1979
  - Arthur D. Little, Inc., 1969 (Box 2a, Folder 82)
  - ASH Council of Executive Office Reorganization, 1970 (Box 2a, Folder 83)
  - ASH Council on Executive Office Reorganization, 1970 (Box 2b, Folder 84-86)
  - Departmental Management in Federal Government, 1969 (Box 2b, Folder 87)
  - Economic Commission on Africa Seminars, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 88-89)
  - Energy Panel, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 90-91)
  - Energy Security Corporation, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Executive Branch Reorganization, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 93-97)
  - Federal Credit Programs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Government Operations Committee, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 99-101)
  - Income Security Systems, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Iran Public Sector Management Project, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 103-109)
  - Legislative Veto, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Organizational Change, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 111-113)
  - Panama Canal, 1975 (Box 3a, Folder 114)
  - Public Enterprise, 1976 (Box 3a, Folder 115-116)
  - Puerto Rico Reorganization, 1976 (Box 3a, Folder 117-119)
  - Space Shuttle, 1958-1969 (Box 3a, Folder 120)
  - United States Railway Association, 1975 (Box 3a, Folder 121)
  - Watergate Reorganization & Reform Act, 1975 (Box 3a, Folder 122)
- Series III: Writings, 1930-1980
  - "Touring through France and Switzerland with a Bicycle," American Motorist and Bicyclist, 1930 April (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - "Two Redheads—Danger," Top Notch Magazine, 1930 October (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Promotion for upcoming "Labor Racketeers" article, The Nation, 1933 August 9 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - "Labor Racketeering: How Corrupt Unions have Betrayed the Rank and File," The Nation, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - "New Labor Leaders Needed: The A.F. of L. and its Racketeers," The Nation, 1933 October 8 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - "The Guaranteed Mortgage Racket," The Nation, 1934 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - "The International Implications of Italian Fascism," Master's Thesis, Brown University, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - "How Radical are College Students?" The American Scholar, 1935 Summer (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - "Labor Racketeering—Who's Racket?" Common Sense, 1938 April (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - "Investigating Municipal Administration", 1938 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - "Facts Save Money," The American City, 1943 July (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - "Racketeers in White," Medical Economics, 1943 September (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - "Racketeers in White," Survey Graphic, 1943 August (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - "Credit Counseling for Employees," Personnel Journal, 1943 September; (2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - "City Hall Looks to the Colleges," National Municipal Review, 1944 February (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - "Investigator and Investigatee," Public Administration Review, 1944 Summer (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - "Reorganization de la Rama Ejecutiva del Gobierno de Colombia", 1950 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - "The Theory of Autonomous Government Corporation: A Critical Appraisal," Public Administration Review, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - "The Government Corporation: Elements of a Model Charter", 1953 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - "La Corporacion del Gobierno, Organizacion y Controles", 1954 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - "The Government Corporation: Organization and Controls," Public Administration Review, 1954 Summer (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - "The Government Corporation in the United States," Public Administration, 1959 Summer (Box 4, Folder 144-145)
  - "Le Impresi Pubbliche Negali Stati Uniti", 1965 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - "Organizational Relationships and Control of Public Enterprise," Selected Papers from Organization And Administration of Public Enterprises, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - "Public Services Organization: An American Perspective," Administration, 1969 Winter (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - "Public Services Organization: An American Perspective," [excerpt], 1969 (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - "Use of Experts and Consultants," International Review of Administrative Science, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - "Response: New Aspects for Attention," Public Administration Review, 1970 May/June (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Reviews, Politics, Position and Power, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - "SASHEP: Accreditation of Health and Educational Programs," Part 1—Working papers, 1971 October (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - "Crisis of Confidence in Government," reprint from The Political Quarterly, 1972 January/March (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - U.S. Space Transportation in the 1980s: Organizational Alternatives, Panel Report, 1977 June (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - "Non-Profit Intermediaries: Symptom or Cure?" Government Sponsored Non-Profits, 1978 November (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - "The Blurred Boundaries of Public Administration," Public Administration Review, 1980 March/April (Box 5, Folder 157)
- Series IV: Research Files, undated
  - History: Evolution of Government Agencies (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - Organization Theory
    - Hoover and Brownlow (Box 5, Folder 159)
    - Classical (Box 5, Folder 160)
    - Behavioralists and Psychologists (Box 5, Folder 161)
    - Authority, Coordination, Values (Box 5, Folder 162)
    - The New Dimensions-Critique (Box 5, Folder 163)
    - General (Box 5, Folder 164)
  - Reorganization
    - History (Box 5, Folder 165)
    - Uses, Purposes and Limitations (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Organization and Policy: Interest Groups (Box 5, Folder 167)
  - President
    - Role and Style, part I (Box 5, Folder 168)
    - Role and Style, part II (Box 5, Folder 169)
    - Relationship to Congress (Box 5, Folder 170)
    - Relationship to Agencies and Bureaucracy (Box 5, Folder 171)
    - Outside Constituencies (Box 5, Folder 172)
    - Executive Office (Box 5, Folder 173)
    - General (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Congress
    - Culture and Organization (Box 5, Folder 175)
    - Role of Committees (Box 5, Folder 176)
    - Role as Legislator (Box 5, Folder 177)
    - Role as Administrator (Box 5, Folder 178)
    - Relationship to Executive Department (Box 5, Folder 179)
    - Interest Groups (Box 5, Folder 180)
    - Attitude toward Local Officials (Box 5, Folder 181)
    - Views on Organizational Structure (Box 5, Folder 182)
  - Coordination
    - Definition and Analysis (Box 5, Folder 183)
    - Non-Organizational Approach (Box 5, Folder 184)
    - Cost Cutting Programs (Box 5, Folder 185)
  - Institutional Behavior and Personality (Box 5, Folder 186)
  - Intergovernmental Relations
    - Part I (Box 6, Folder 187)
    - Part II (Box 6, Folder 188)
    - Examples (Box 6, Folder 189-194)
  - Agriculture: Little Local Governments, Grass Roots, Para-governments (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - Corporations (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - Typology
    - Executive Departments (Box 6, Folder 197)
    - Independent Agencies (Box 6, Folder 198)
    - Government Corporations (Box 6, Folder 199)
    - Captive Corporations (Box 6, Folder 200)
    - Boards and Commissions (Box 6, Folder 201)
    - Research Institutes (Box 6, Folder 202)
    - Interagency and Advisory Committees (Box 6, Folder 203)
    - Interagency Committees (Box 6, Folder 204)
    - Coordinators and Ministers without portfolio (Box 6, Folder 205)
    - Intergovernmental bodies (Box 6, Folder 206)
  - Case Study
    - Natural Resources (Box 6, Folder 207)
    - Banking (Box 6, Folder 208)
    - Archives (Box 6, Folder 209)
    - Atomic Energy (Box 6, Folder 210)
    - Transportation (Box 6, Folder 211)
    - District of Columbia (Box 7, Folder 212)
    - Locomotive Inspection (Box 7, Folder 213)
    - Urban Development (Box 7, Folder 214)
    - Foreign Aid (Box 7, Folder 215)
    - Health, Education and Welfare (Box 7, Folder 216)
    - Commerce and Labor (Box 7, Folder 217)
    - Poverty (Box 7, Folder 218)
  - Departmental Management (Box 7, Folder 219-223)
  - Institutional Personality (Box 7, Folder 224-227)
  - Policy-Institutional Memory (Box 7, Folder 228)
  - Professions (Box 7, Folder 229)
  - Executive Branch Reorganization (Box 7, Folder 230-231)
  - Evaluation of the Bureau of the Budget (Box 7, Folder 232)
  - Citizen Participation (Box 7, Folder 233)
  - Judicial System (Box 7, Folder 234)
  - Book review (Box 7, Folder 235)
- Series V: Personal, undated
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 7, Folder 236-237)
  - Inmates' Commissaries Survey, undated (Box 7, Folder 238)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 7, Folder 239-240)
  - Newsclippings, undated (Box 7, Folder 241)
  - Oral History Interview transcript, undated (Box 7, Folder 242)
  - Pen [see also Box 2b], undated (Box 7, Folder 243)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 244)
  - 3+ copies, undated (Box 8, Folder 245)
  - "We're All Working for the Penn Central," by Branford Taylor, undated (Box 8, Folder 246)